Finding aid to the Quentin Quesnell papers CA.MS.00379
Smith College Archives
Quentin Quesnell papers
1927-2012
1970 - 2000
Smith College Archives
Quesnell, Quentin
CA.MS.00379
2.292 linear feet (3 containers)
Faculty. Head of the Department of Religion from 1975 to 1997. The papers contain biographical materials including a complete bibliography, correspondence, notes, photographs, publications and research.
Biographical / Historical
Born on February 27, 1927 in Milwaukee, Wisconsin, Quesnell earned a Master's Degree in Philosophy and an STL from St. Louis University. He later did studies in eastern languages and the Bible in Vienna, Paris, Jerusalem, and Rome. After receiving a PhD in Sacred Scriptures from the Pontifical Biblical Institute, he joined Marquette University as a professor (1966 - 1972). He left Marquette for Smith College, becoming the head of the Department of religion from 1975 until 1997. During his time at Smith, Quesnell met fellow professor Jean Higgins and the two married in 1973. After retirement in 1997, he was awarded the Roe Straut Professor Emeritus (Roe Straut Professor of Humanities, 1988).
Quesnell actively engaged in several scholarly debates throughout his lifetime but is most known for his role in the Mar Saba Letter debate and his subsequent high-profile disputes with the discoverer letter, Morton Smith (1915 - 1991). In 1973 Smith published two books on his discovery of a previously unknown letter written by Clement of Alexandria to "Theodore" regarding a secret gospel of Mark. Quesnell's initial skepticism of the authenticity of this discovery sparked a 30-year debate within the academic community.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains correspondence, photographic prints and slides, publications, research and Quesnell's professional file.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into five series:
Correspondence
Professional Life
Publications
Research
Oversized Materials
Conditions Governing Access
Except where noted in the finding aid, the papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Smith College Archives.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Quentin Quesnell Papers, 1927 - 2012 were created by Quentin Quesnell and donated over a period of two (2) years to the College Archives.
Related Materials
42. Faculty - Quesnell, Jean Higgins
52. Department of Religion
Separated Materials
Additional unprocessed materials are housed in fourteen (14) record center cartons measuring fourteen (14) linear feet. A preliminary inventory is available. Please contact the Smith College Archives for more information.
Bible -- Study and teaching (Higher) - Massachusetts -- Northampton.; Hapax legomenon.; Hebrew language -- Lexicology.; Literary forgeries and mystifications - Early works to 1800.; Mar Saba (Monastery); Secret Gospel according to Mark.; Writing -- Identification.; 35mm; correspondence; drafts (documents); manuscripts for publication; photographic prints; Quesnell, Quentin, 1927 -- 2012.; Smith College. Department of Religion and Biblical Literature.; Smith, Morton, 1915 -- 1991.
- Series I: Correspondence
  - Brown, Scott, 1994 - 2003 (Box 989.6, Folder 1)
  - Brown, Scott (thesis), 1994 - 2003 (Box 989.6, Folder 2)
  - editorial materials, 1970 - 2000 (Box 989.6, Folder 3)
  - Fish, Dick, 1990 - 1995 (Box 989.6, Folder 4)
  - Paananen, Timo, 2009 - 2011 (Box 989.6, Folder 5)
  - Quesnell, Jean Higgins, 1983 (Box 989.6, Folder 6)
  - Smith, Morton, 1970 - 1985 (Box 989.6, Folder 7)
  - various scholars, 1975 - 2005 (Box 989.6, Folder 8)
- Series II: Professional Life
  - Smith College, 1994 - 2003 (Box 989.6, Folder 9)
- Series III: Publications
  - "An Amusing Pericope", 1994 (Box 989.6, Folder 10)
  - "Internal of the Literary Analysis", 1975 - 1989 (Box 989.6, Folder 11)
  - "The Mar Saba Clementine: A Question of Evidence", 1973 - 1985 (Box 989.6, Folder 12)
  - "A New Gospel Story and It's Explanation", 1975 - 1990 (Box 989.6, Folder 13)
  - "A Note On Overkill", undated (Box 989.6, Folder 14)
  - (review) "The Secret Gospel: The Discovery and Interpretation of the Secret Gospel According to Mark", 197 (Box 989.6, Folder 15)
- Series IV: Research
  - handwriting analysis, undated (Box 989.7, Folder 16)
  - Hapax legomenon, undated (Box 989.7, Folder 17)
  - notes: A - H, undated (Box 989.7, Folder 18)
  - notes: I -N, undated (Box 989.7, Folder 19)
  - notes: O - Z, undated (Box 989.7, Folder 20)
  - notes: untitled, undated (Box 989.7, Folder 21)
  - notes: 2009 (Box 989.7, Folder 22)
  - Professional Development Fund, 1987 - 1988 (Box 989.7, Folder 23)
- Series V: Oversized Materials
  - (3) 8" x 11" photographs, unknown manuscript, 1988 (Box 989.8)
  - (33) 11" x 14" photographs, unknown manuscript, 1988 (Box 989.8)
  - (3) slides of a stone fish, sent by Dick Fish (see Correspondence), 1995 (Box 989.8)
  - ( 9 ) slides; "unknown manuscript", 1983 (Box 989.8)
  - ( 3 ) slides; shelfmark, "VD v18"; by Garo Nalbandian, 1983 (Box 989.8)
  - ( 4) slides; title page, "Bibliotheque Maj. Coll. 1776"; by Garo Nalbandian, 1983 (Box 989.8)
  - ( 3 ) slides; colophon, "Isacci Vossii de septuaginta interpretibus corumpque tralatione atque chronologia dissertatione"; by Garo Nalbandian, 1983 (Box 989.8)
  - ( 4 ) slides; title page, "Gerardi Ioannis Vossii harmoniae evangelicae de passion, morte, resurrection atque ascension Jesu Christi salvatoris nostri"; by Garo Nalbandian, 1983 (Box 989.8)
  - ( 2 ) slides; front endpaper, "Nota pro domina ad Xbre 1735", "Nota pro Marehesina Julio 1737", unknown manuscript; by Garo Nalbandian, 1983 (Box 989.8)